Guide to the Margery Bailey Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Margery Bailey papers
1912-1994
SC0020
Bailey, Margery, 1891-1963
3.25 Linear feet
Correspondence with actors, actresses, theatrical people, dramatists and writers; materials relating to the English Club and the Dramatists Alliance at Stanford, the Shakespeare Festival at Ashland, Oregon, the Institute of Renaissance Studies, and theater productions at Stanford, 1935-36; letters to former students Robert A. Brauns, Myna B. Hughes, H. Arthur Klein, Thomas Seller, and Grace Margaret Webster, 1930-63, collected by Phillip Persky for his edition of "Letters of Margery Bailey," SAN JOSE STUDIES; photocopies of Bailey correspondence regarding John P. Marquand, Clarence Darrow, Gertrude Stein, Robinson Jeffers, Irvin S. Cobb, and Harold Bell Wright; and an unpublished article by Frank de Guerre. Material about Miss Bailey's work includes term papers of her students, her own papers as a student, lecture and research notes, reprints of her articles and papers on the humanities at Stanford.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of estate of Margery Bailey, 1964; gift of Phillip Persky, 2002; photocopies gift of Robert Gros.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Alternative Formats
Materials pertaining to John P. Marquand, Clarence Darrow, Gertrude Stein, Robinson Jeffers, Irvin S. Cobb, and Harold Bell Wright are photocopies of originals in private hands.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Margery Bailey was a professor of English at Stanford University from 1914-1963. She was active in Stanford dramatics and was involved in the Oregon Shakespeare Festival at Ashland, Orgeon as both an actress and as a director.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence with actors, actresses, theatrical people, dramatists and writers; materials relating to the English Club and the Dramatists Alliance at Stanford, the Shakespeare Festival at Ashland, Oregon, the Institute of Renaissance Studies, and theater productions at Stanford, 1935-36; letters to former students Robert A. Brauns, Myna B. Hughes, H. Arthur Klein, Thomas Seller, and Grace Margaret Webster, 1930-63, collected by Phillip Persky for his edition of "Letters of Margery Bailey," SAN JOSE STUDIES; photocopies of Bailey correspondence regarding John P. Marquand, Clarence Darrow, Gertrude Stein, Robinson Jeffers, Irvin S. Cobb, and Harold Bell Wright; and an unpublished article by Frank de Guerre. Material about Miss Bailey's work includes term papers of her students, her own papers as a student, lecture and research notes, reprints of her articles and papers on the humanities at Stanford.
Access Terms
Bailey, Margery, 1891-1963; Brauns, Robert A.; Cobb, Irvin Shrewsbury, 1876-1944.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Hughes, Myna B.; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Klein, H. Arthur.; Marquand, John P. (John Phillips), 1893-1960.; Oregon Shakespearian Festival.; Persky, Phillip.; Seller, Thomas; Stanford University. Department of Speech and Drama. Faculty.; Stanford University. Dramatists Alliance.; Stanford University. English Club.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.; Webster, Grace Margaret.; Wright, Harold Bell, 1872-1944.; Actors.; Class notes.; College teachers.; College theater.; Dramatics.; Lecture notes.; Letters.; Research notes.; Theater.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Julia Cooley Altrocchi (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Maxwell Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Fay Bainter (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Judith Bloch (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aldo Bozzini (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gilmore Brown (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ed Brubaker (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ernest Callenbach (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Katherine Cornell (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Norman Corwin (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jane Cowl (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. George Creel (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. Lester Denney (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alice Dennis (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Andre Ferrier (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thomas Ferte (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Gould Fletcher (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lynn Fontanne (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Golden (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - J. C. MacDonald Hay (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Helen Hayes (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Polly Damrosch Howard (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Eli Jaffe (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert Edmond Jones (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Walter F. Kerr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alfred Kreymborg (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dilys Bennett Laing (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert Tyler Lee (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Edgar Lee Masters (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David W. Maurer (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Burgess Meredith (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ronald E. Mitchell (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Baldwin McGaw (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - N. Richard Nusbaum (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Philip Pearce (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gregory Peck (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Josephine Peck (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert R. Presnell, Sr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Herman Shumlin (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cornelia Otis Skinner (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Betty Smith (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - C. Aubrey Smith (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Steinbeck (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John van Druten (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Orson Welles (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ann Stanford White (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William A. P. Stanley (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert Gros photocopies of manuscripts of the following writers: John P. Marquand, John P. Marquand, Clarence Darrow, Gertrude Stein, Robinson Jeffers, Irvin S. Cobb, Harold Bell Wright (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters of recommendation written by M. Bailey (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memos and letters anent review of courses, assignments, etc, for S. U. Dept. of English, 1942-44 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Survey of the quality of the compositions of Stanford students, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dramatists' Alliance: history and related papers, 1935-56, including letter to Cyril Clemens, Sept. 28, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dramatists' Alliance: photographs (Box 1, Folder 10A)
  - Dramatists' Alliance: photographs (Box 1, Folder 10B)
  - Dramatists' Alliance: miscellaneous papers (Box 1A, Folder 11)
  - Views on undergraduate education: teaching vs. research, 1954-55 (Box 1A, Folder 12)
  - Veterans Theater of the Air (Box 1A, Folder 13)
  - Music of Southern Americas, 1943 (Box 1A, Folder 14)
  - Frank de Guerre: unpublished article "David Belasco as I know him" (Box 1A, Folder 15)
  - Term papers submitted to M. Bailey (Box 1A, Folder 16)
  - English Club - history (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pageant book of the English production of Service, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1948 Shakespeare Festival of Oregon (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1949 Shakespeare Festival of Oregon (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Institute of Renaissance Studies & Shakespeare Festival Association, 1959-62 (includes class records and final examinations) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Course in Shakespearean production at Stanford, summer 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Shakespeare Guilde of America, 1946-47 production of Othello based on 1935 Stanford production (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Course in stage classics production at Stanford, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Notes, articles, etc., from a file marked "Old Papers" and covering Boswell, Chaucer, dialect, Frankenstein, Jonson, Osborn, Sierra, ballads, Pope, novels, Bunyan, and Ossian. (Box 3)
  - Printed material by and about M. Bailey (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Unpublished manuscripts: "The man of the world" (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Manuscript on Celtic origins (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Bound volume of tests taken by Bailey as a Stanford student, 1912-1913 (Box 4)
  - Copy of Bailey's book Whistle for Good Fortune (Box 4)
  - Sample notebook of M. Bailey (Box 4)
  - Addenda, March 1966 and April 1994
    - Letters: Bailey to James S. Sandoe, 1944-55 (41); Sandoe to Bailey, 1937-51 (65); Bailey to Wallace Stegner, 1950 (1) (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Foreign letters," 1927-28. Handwritten and typed copies. Some by M. Bailey, some inidentified; written while on European sojourn. (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - "The Amateur Traveler" by Bailey (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Notebook of Bailey (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Letters of Margery Bailey," San Jose Studies, Winter 1991 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Manuscript music for several songs written by Bailey, 1945 and undated, with a letter from James Lawson, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 33)